Merchaphiles are non- ant organisms that
closely associate with ants. From those
who infiltrate ant colonies and secretly
feed on them, those who are farmed by
the ants as livestock, and those who
enslave ants to do their bidding.
[music] Today, I'm going to explain
every type of Merchafilly found in
nature, as well as the increasingly
insane ways ants exploit each other.
Let's start with ant farms. And I don't
mean humans farming ants. I mean ants
engaging in agriculture. These are
aphids, small true bugs that drain many
plants for food. As a byproduct, they
release a rich sugary substance called
honeydew, a great food source for
[music] ants. Ants will milk aphids,
rubbing their sides with their antenna,
causing them to secrete a droplet of
honeydew. In exchange, [music] the
aphids enjoy the protection of the ants.
Common aphid predators like ladybugs and
hoverflies will be ruthlessly attacked
by ants to keep them away. Ants will
sometimes even pick up and carry aphids
into their nests where they've
constructed stables, rooms to keep their
herds of livestock safe and [music] to
breed them. When the colony moves to
reestablish their nest at a new
location, they'll carry aphid eggs with
them to ensure they can spawn a new
herd. Leaf cutter ants are factory
farmers and instead of taking care of
another animal, grow and tend to an
everpresent fungus. The workers will go
out and chop up pieces of leaves to
bring back to their nest, which the
fungus can grow on. Then the leaf
[music] cutters use pieces of the
mcelium as the only source of food for
themselves and [music] their larae. The
fungus breaks down plant polymers that
leaf cutters don't have the digestive
enzymes for, making it a sort [music] of
external stomach for the colony to
survive. Likewise, the fungus is unable
to survive without the tending of the
ants. Leaf cutters will clean debris,
lay nutritious feces, [music] and lick
away foreign spores to keep the fungus
in tip-top shape. When a leaf cutter
queen [music] journeys off to start her
own colony, she will carry a small clone
of the royal fungus, and together they
shall raise a kingdom of their own. To
complete the ukareotic trifecta, ants
also farm plants. Ant gardens are
structures formed high up on tree
canopies made of leaves, vegetable
fibers, and of course, feces. These are
the perfect constructions to grow
epipites, plants that grow off of other
plants. Several ant species will bring
seeds from epipitic plants to deposit
into their gardens. In Fiji, ant gardens
can grow about six species of plants in
total, while neotropical ant gardens can
have up to 78 different species of
plants. While some of these plants do
provide sources of food, another huge
benefit for the ant farmers is a
structural one. These ants live inside
[music] of the plants that they grow,
using these sprawling roots and fruing
bodies as a framework for their nests.
Ant agriculture allows colonies to
[music] support population sizes that
wouldn't be possible otherwise, allowing
them to take over extremely large
[music] regions, which is exactly what
happened when humans started farming as
well. The consistent and mass production
of food allowed us to hold much larger
populations in [music] one place,
kickstarting the global coordinated
civilizations we have today. But while
the human agricultural revolution took
place 12,000 years ago, ants have been
doing this for 60 [music] million years,
since around the time of the asteroid
impact. We think this is why their
farming behavior developed in the first
place. As [music] an adaptation to
surviving in the same harsh environment
that killed most of the dinosaurs, ants
have been around for 150 million years
after all. With such a long evolutionary
history, they've had many generations to
adapt [music] and diversify, developing
complex cast systems, reproductive
abilities found in no other organism and
organized behaviors to construct massive
nests or march to war. But that also
means there's been a lot of time for
other organisms to adapt to them. In a
piece of amber, 100 million years old,
is a specimen called an alienate. It's
believed that their closest living
relatives are cockroaches, though some
recent work may put them closer to
mantises. Regardless, their shape
suspiciously [music]
looks like that of an ant, especially
the now extinct ants that existed at the
time. This is perhaps the earliest
example of mercamorphy [music] or ant
mimicry, which is incredibly widespread
today. This ant is wo that's not a
butterface, that's a spiderface. Jumping
spiders in the genus murmury have bodies
that look exactly [music] like ants and
will even wave their front legs to
simulate antenna. Some of them have fake
eye spots on the backs of their heads or
on their jaws to match the eye positions
of various ant [music] species. While
murmuracy spiders live close to the ants
that they mimic, they usually try their
best to avoid contact with them because
[music] really the form is for their own
protection. Ants have large numbers,
strength to lift up to 50 times their
own body weight and often venomous bites
[music] and stings. They can coordinate
to kill large animals including megapaa.
So a lot of predators just innately
avoid them. Thus, physically mimicking
an ant is a common predator defense
strategy in many animals like mirid
[music] true bugs, singogaster flies, or
paricettoid wasps. Mantises and crickets
[music] can mimic ants in their
vulnerable laral stages, then lose this
mimicry once they become adults with
better defense systems [music] they can
rely on. It's even been suggested that
some plants mimic ants. The elongated
spots [music] on this pacifllora flower
are thought to be perceived by
herbivores as similar to ants. Though
there isn't enough evidence to confirm
this to be true, plants mimicking
insects is [music] a thing that happens.
So, it's not outside the realm of
possibility. And this is why we're
pretty sure alonopter were doing the
same thing [music] a 100 million years
ago. Crab spiders though don't do this
for protection, but to sneak up on and
prey on the ants that they mimic.
Aphantailus rejerci mimics sephilodes
ants known for their armored heads which
they [music] use as living doors
plugging holes to keep out intruders. A
reji is known to [music] carry the dead
husks of their models which is thought
to chemically camouflage them helping
them sneak up on ants and quickly hunt
them before they realize they're not
dealing with another ant. Rove beetles
take this one step further by actually
[music] infiltrating a colony and
getting the ants to recognize them as
one of their own. The world of ants is a
chemical one. They release pherommones
and vomit them into each other's mouths
as a form of communication. So, rove
beetles release these same chemicals and
blend in. They also have a similar shape
to ants to sell the illusion further.
Rove beetles will march alongside ants
on raids and live with them as peers.
Then, when they least expect [music] it,
they'll leap onto one of their step
siblings or stepchildren and feed on
them in secret. Rove beetles infiltrate
and exploit [music] the social structure
of ant colonies, making them social
parasites. These are organisms that
don't parasetize an individual's body
like a tapeworm would, but instead
parasetize the super organism that is a
youocial colony. [music] Caterpillars of
the large blue butterfly emit
pherommones and sounds that mimic murmur
queens, [music] instructing worker ants
to bring them back to their nest and
place them with all of the larae. From
here, the caterpillar will do one of two
things. [music]
They'll become a predator, feeding on
the ant larae they've been brought to,
or they'll become a cuckoo, begging the
ants to bring them food. While both
strategies can work and fail, [music]
predator caterpillars appear to be six
times more likely to be detected and
killed than cuckoo [music] caterpillars.
Makes sense. I mean, it's probably less
hard to realize that all of the babies
have suddenly [music] been consumed. But
additionally, the rate of these
caterpillars succeeding depends on the
presence of a queen. In Mermica nests,
[music] if the queen dies, the females
from her eggs will become virgin queens.
Equipped with wings they can use to take
nuptual flight, reproduce, and become
queens of their own. But if the queen is
present, she will instruct nurse workers
to [music] neglect, starve, and bite the
female larae, or sometimes release
suppressive pherommones [music] herself
to restrict the growth of her daughters
and cause them to transition into
workers. It appears that the queen's
presence in doing this also makes it
[music] three times more likely that
large blue caterpillars are detected in
their nests. [music] Meaning the
socially parasitic caterpillar needs to
manage a delicate balance of mimicking
the queen to manipulate the workers and
laying low so as to avoid the allseeing
effects of the queen. This kind of
infiltration also happens to us all the
time because when you browse the
internet, you're constantly vulnerable
to scams, malware, and data leaks,
especially on public networks. And the
best way to prevent this is with
NordVPN, the fastest [music] VPN on the
planet. With a single click, Nord's
Threat Protection Pro will protect you
from various online threats, like fake
shop scams, which look identical to real
online shopping websites, but then take
your money and deliver nothing. Fishing
attempts are also everywhere you go on
the internet. I get tons of fake emails
from brands supposedly wanting to
sponsor my videos, which include a fake
link to their website, which is actually
a dangerous link designed [music] to
steal my data. I've also gotten these on
my school email claiming I haven't paid
my tuition or met my PhD requirements.
Meticulously designed with personal
information about me, all to get me to
click a [music] link. With NordVPN, I
can feel a lot safer. Threat protection
pro stops scams by scanning the websites
you visit and blocking them before they
can cause harm. A regular VPN won't
protect you from scams like these, but
NordVPN will. So, visit
nordvpn.com/daninblue
to get your online traffic protected.
With just one account, you can protect
up to 10 devices with easy to access
apps for all major [music] platforms.
Additionally, with Nord, you can get all
the benefits of a VPN, like setting your
location to wherever you want to be
browsing from, so that even when
traveling, you can stay at home
virtually and not miss out on your
favorite local content. Go to
nordvpn.com/danblue
to get an exclusive deal and four extra
months free. It's completely [music]
risk-free with Nord's 30-day money back
guarantee. And if you experience any
problems, their 247 customer support
will help you whenever you need. That's
nordvpn.com/danblue
to cover all your cyber security needs.
Back to the video. Adafilla cockroaches
are small and sneak into the nests of
leaf cutter ants by hitchhiking on the
leaves they carry or on the ants
themselves. Once they're inside, by
mimicking odor to prevent being
attacked, they feed on the leaves and on
the royal fungus. But no one is better
at socially parasetizing ants than ants.
A queen bothmic decapitants allows
herself to be dragged by taponoma
workers into their nest. From here, she
makes her way onto the top of the much
larger local queen's back and slowly
saws her head off. After the head goes
pop, the invading queen lays her own
eggs. And amazingly, the tapanoma
workers start [music] to take care of
them, helping to raise a colony of an
entirely different species, then dying
out when they're no longer needed. This
is called inquillinism, where one
species of ant enters another's colony,
then depends on them for their
development and growth. And it doesn't
have to involve death to the queen of
Scots or the usurping of a colony.
Acrommex's insinuator [music] is kind of
like an adapila cockroach. The queen
through a method that is still
undetermined ends up in the nest of
Acromem's Akinitior. These are both leaf
cutters, by the way. Here, the
insinuator queen and workers will
consume the royal fungus while not
helping out with the chores and leaving
Akiniors to do all the work of
maintaining it. They're basically a
species of leaf cutter that's evolved to
be a deadbeat bum. Mooching only so much
they need to survive, but not so much
that the original colony won't. These
kidnapper ants are raiding the nest of
another [music] species for one
particular reason, to steal their
babies. They have mandibles specially
evolved to grab pupé, which are taken
back to their own nest and imprinted
upon with the kidnapper's [music]
scent. When the babies grow up, they
have no idea that they're surrounded by
a different species. They're completely
brainwashed [music] and so immediately
get to work and start to forage for
food. This is called dulosis or slave
making. Another kind of permanent social
parasetism where instead of invading and
staying in the nest of a different
species, you capture a different species
and enslave them back at your own nest.
Slave ant [music] mandibles tend to be
serrated, which is great for chewing
food. While kidnapper ant mandibles are
pretty much only good for stealing
babies and are very badly shaped for
chewing. So, the kidnappers rely on
their captives to chew their food and
regurgitate it into their mouths. The
captives also do all the other work
around the colony like fixing the nest
and taking care of the young. Meanwhile,
the kidnappers loaf around in a big pile
until it's time to raid again,
offloading all of the work onto their
unrelated brainwashed [music] minions.
These social parasetisms have evolved
over 60 times in ants independently. And
it [music] seems that the common pattern
here is that socially parasitic species
are closely related to their host
species. This is Emory's rule, a theory
that states that ants [music] of the
same species will be more likely to
interact and after enough time diverge
into separate species where one has
specialized to take advantage of the
other. Camponotus furidanis and
camponotus planetus [music] can cohabit
the same nests. But sometimes one
species begins to dominate food
distribution over the other. This could
be a snapshot of what a transitional
stage between cooperation and social
parasetism might look like in ants. Of
course, ants have physical parasites,
too. Roundorms often infect [music] the
inside of ants and burst out of them
like aliens, but they do that for like
everything. Forward flies target worker
ants and lay their eggs inside them.
From there, the larae will consume the
ant from the inside and crawl up to
their head. Pop the head, clean [music]
off, and hatch out of it. The mightilies
retinary attaches itself to the foot of
an ant to drain its hemoly. Strangely,
their rear legs actually [music] mimic
the ant's tarsel claws, allowing the ant
to use the might as their foot. By doing
this, the might [music] can live
comfortably undetected with a steady
source of nutrition, a whole new level
of foot stuff. This is [music] a beetle
that's instead into butt stuff by
latching onto an ant and basically
becoming a second abdomen. In a kind of
similar twist, the inqualine ant
tetramorium inquilinum has been
described as the ultimate parasitic
[music] ant. The queen will enter a nest
and make her way onto the much larger
local queen. She'll latch onto her and
then that's it. She doesn't lay any
workers because all of her eggs become
other queens that hop onto the host
queen and just sit there or presumably
leave. We don't know much about their
life cycle. Of course, we can't talk
about ant parasites without talking
about zombies. Tropical carpenter ants
live high up in tree canopies and travel
across an extensive network of sky
bridges. But sometimes, in order to
cover difficult gaps, the ants have to
descend to the dangerous forest floor.
Here, the spores of the fungus
ofiocortisps unilateralis can attach to
their exoskeletons [music] and spread
through them, causing ants to spasm
while climbing and fall back to the
forest floor. From here, the ant is
completely mind controlled by the
fungus, being forced to climb up the
stem of a plant exactly 26 cm above the
forest floor, clamp on tightly with
their backs facing north in an
environment with 95% humidity and
temperatures between 20 and 30° C, the
perfect conditions for the fungus to
reproduce. From here, the fruing bodies
rupture out of the ant's head and
release spores [music] to start the life
cycle once again. Because the zombie
ants are driven to these optimal
conditions, of cortiseps reproductive
sites end up being covered in
graveyards. Thousands of dead ants
holding on to various plants. This is
also the fungus that Cortiseps in the
Last of Us is based off of, which takes
over the world by turning us into
mushroom zombies. Now, let's take a
break from parasites because predators
need some love, too. Giant anteaters use
their large claws to uncover the nests
of ants and termites. From here, they
press their thin [music] trunks in and
launch out a 2-ft long sticky tongue,
which picks up any ants it comes across.
They spam this maneuver at 150 times
[music] a minute, quick enough to avoid
the stings of angry ants. Giant
anteaters spend about [music] 1 minute
at a nest before moving on, and can
visit up to 200 nests in a day,
consuming over 35,000 ants to meet their
daily caloric requirements. Several
animals are Merchapes, [music] evolved
specifically to consume ants. Ants are
extremely plentiful. There is an
estimated 20 quadrillion of them in the
world, or 2.5 million ants for every
human. Out of all terrestrial animals in
the world, ants make up to 20% of the
total biomass. So, if you can adapt to
reliably eat them, there are few better
food sources. This hollow cone in the
ground is the masterpiece of an ant lion
who's perfectly crafted the angle to be
just enough that the sand barely [music]
stays from slipping. When an ant walks
onto it, the sand will collapse, causing
the ant to tumble to the bottom, where
the ant lion waits with its massive
mandibles exposed. [music] If this trap
fails to make the ant fall in, the ant
lion will flick sand, avalanching it
back down. Worm lions are an unrelated
organism that have evolved to do the
exact same thing, [music] creating
conicle pits in the sand that they use
to ambush ants that fall in. Once
they've drained the ant hole, they yeet
the empty carcass away. Alvareza are a
family of small dinosaurs that have long
tube-shaped snouts [music] and tiny
teeth, implying they were insectovores
that stuck their mouths into insect
filled holes. Their stout arms and
compact hands suggest that they dug
through dirt, [music] much like
anteaters do with their claws. And so
it's been interpreted that these
dinosaurs might have been mercapaging
[music]
heavily on ant and termite nests. But of
course, there are also ants that will
only eat ants. Clonal raider ants are
parthonogenic, which means the females
asexually clone themselves, and so
they're all females. They don't have
queens or even a home nest, [music] and
instead spend all of their time marching
from colony to colony to invade and
consume them. There are so many crazy
ant- on ant interactions that it
probably deserves its own video. Let me
know if you want that or maybe just a
youocialism video in general. But I
wanted to highlight something incredible
that was only discovered a few months
ago. Earlier this year, the ant Messor
Abericus was discovered to do something
crazy. The queens produce offspring of
their own species, but also offspring of
a different species. And I don't just
mean a different morph. They literally
give birth to Messor structure, a
species of ant that exists on its own
and diverged from M Aaricus over 5
million years ago. A queen Abericus will
intake the sperm of a structure, but
then she won't pass her own genetic
material into it and instead somehow
clone the structure while laying the
eggs of her own species separately. But
she also mixes the structure sperm with
her own genetic material, creating large
numbers of hybrid workers, which are
stronger and healthier than either of
the purebred ants. This process has been
called xenop parody and it's unclear how
it evolved or how it fully works. Though
that's true for so many things about
ants. I wouldn't even be surprised if
there were some ants watching this
video. Here are some subscribe
pherommones.
Uh if you're not an ant you should
subscribe to. Acacia ants live inside
acacia trees in their domatia structures
grown for the insects to [music]
inhabit. The acacas also provide
nectaries to feed the adults and
nutritious pods to feed the larae.
Herbivores that want to eat the acacia
are rapidly attacked by acacia ants,
including [music] giraffes and
elephants, which the ants will
successfully drive away. Sometimes ants
will even chop up plants that grow near
the acacia that might be stealing too
much of its [music] sunlight. Ingga
trees have a similar relationship to
big-headed ants, except these guys might
not be as loyal. Nymphidia caterpillars
can pass through harsh ant security by
secretreting nectar of their own from
their backsides [music] which the ants
will prefer and then allow the
caterpillars's passage to consume the
tree they promised to protect. Those
sellouts. There are many plants with
long co-evolutionary [music]
relationships with ants called
mercapites. Some will harbor ants and
use them for defense, but sometimes they
simply [music] attract or grow near ants
to absorb the nutrients of dead ants and
the husks of their prey. Some plants use
ants as a method of [music] seed
dispersal. They create daspores, seeds
with a nutritious eliome attached. The
elioomes are perfect food for ant larae.
And so the ants will bring the daspor
back [music] to their nest, feed the
eliome to their larae, then discard the
seed, which helps it reach a much
[music] more favorable location. This
process has independently evolved over
100 times, a testament [music] to how
stable and reliable ants can be. In
fact, eggs of the giant prickly stick
insect mimic seeds that ants will
naturally disperse, promoting the eggs
to be picked up and carried by the ants
to help these stick bugs emerge in a
favorable [music] location.
Additionally, the newly hatched larae
mimic leptomex ants. Now, not every
mercaphilic relationship needs [music]
to be beautifully mutualistic or
terribly parasitic. There are many
commensalists that live alongside ants
for their own sake, but don't harm or
help them in [music] any way, like ant
crickets, which mimic ant pherommones
just to exist inside a colony, as well
as hundreds of others, flies, [music]
beetles, snails, and many undescribed
organisms. Ant nests are a pretty safe
place to stay if you want to avoid
predators. Plus, you don't have to pay
for utilities because the ants control
the heat and humidity levels for the
queen and their larae. So, with the cost
of living nowadays, it may be optimal to
move to an ant nest. Though, that's
assuming your nest doesn't get visited
by an army. Just like the clonal raiders
from earlier, army ants are nomadic and
go around murdering everything in their
path. Nearly nothing stands a chance
against the sheer numbers and
aggressiveness of these massive swarms.
So, when scouts of different colonies
find army ants, they report back to the
nest where they begin picking up their
larae and evacuating entirely. But of
course, many ants don't back down in the
face of an oncoming army and decide to
prepare for siege warfare. They fortify
their walls, sealing off [music] the
entrances to their nest. But the army
ants are preparing as well. Because they
don't have a place to call home, every
night, army ants build pop-up shelters
out of their own bodies called bivoax,
which protect the queen and larae at the
center. Hundreds of thousands of ants
linked together to form these castles of
their flesh and of some [music] ticks
pretending to be their feet. Come
daytime, they are well-rested and ready
to begin charging out in raiding
formations. Now, thanks to their
agriculturally supported [music] huge
colony sizes, leaf cutters are of few
ants that have enough resources to
reliably defeat oncoming [music] army
ants. They've even evolved a specialized
cast of soldier ant, large roided out
weapons of war. Smaller workers will
grab the invaders by their legs, holding
them down so that the soldiers can slice
their heads clean off with their
mandibles. Only one species of army
antmax essenti is known to attack fully
matured leaf cutter colonies and be able
to succeed. Other new social species get
invaded by ants as well. And typically
bees and wasps get completely
obliterated. [music]
But termites can at least have a
fighting chance. I'll save termites for
their own video, but they have very cool
soldier casts and organized behaviors to
allow for complex war tactics, and many
of them regularly battle ants. Here's a
video of ant and termite soldiers in
what appears to be a truce or a
standstill, each with a line of guards
facing each other to block off their own
territories. Next thing you know,
they're going to be exchanging gifts on
Christmas. Non-armmy ants also go to war
with each other. And the levels of this
get truly insane. It involves the
coordinated effort of entire colonies or
sometimes several colonies allying with
each other. It can end with one side
fleeing or being destroyed, but can also
end in stalemate or in a peace treaty.
Sometimes a party will win by killing
the rival queen, then adopt the
surviving enemies into their own
faction. And I'm sure there are tons
[music] more ant tactics, antics that
we've never observed that are happening
right now. Argentine ants are known for
their behavior of forming super
colonies, a collection of separated ant
colonies, all working in coordination
with [music] each other. Workers and
queens are free to travel and stay
between the different nests, allowing
them to span [music] continents in their
range. Argentine ant super colonies were
reported in California in 2000, then in
Europe in 2002, Japan in 2009, and
Australia in 2010. And upon further
analysis, these continental super
[music] colonies appeared to be
genetically similar at every single
interval, suggesting that they were all
a part of one global super colony,
making them the most populous animal
[music] society in the world. But the
sun never sets on the Angentine Empire
because parts of the global colony have
broken off and formed their own super
colonies, causing infighting on an
international scale. Additionally, some
other ants like red fire [music] ants
have also formed super colonies and have
been capable of seizing large chunks of
territory back from the Argentine
Empire. These super colonies present a
huge problem for other wildlife. In
California, Argentine ants have killed
up to 90% of the native ant species,
[music] and they've also driven away
many other insects as well. They also
happen to be aphid farmers, meaning they
are huge pests for the native plants and
for our agriculture. And all of this
happened because of us. The reason that
these super colonies formed in the first
place is because of our transatlantic
transportation. Unintentionally
harboring some of these ants. We brought
them across the ocean where they didn't
face the same tough competition. And so
we're able to expand everywhere and
invade [clears throat] everything. And
it's something that humans are trying to
work on stopping. Even on a smaller
scale, there are many human ant
interactions because as we've seen, ants
are very adaptable. We've changed the
world in numerous ways and so they've
changed in tow. Many ants rely on our
walls as their palaces, our sidewalk
trash as their ambrosia, and our
watering lawns as their fountains of
life. Some are attracted to electrical
equipment, our farms, and our homes
causing billions of dollars in damage.
I'm careful to clean up crumbs just
because of ants, only for every summer
to realize, "Ah, [__] there are ants
everywhere." But there are also things
to appreciate about ants as well. In
many parts of the world, ants are
enjoyed as a high protein delicacy or as
a cultural food. In Colombia, leaf
cutter ant pincers were used as stitches
for open [music] wounds. People also
just find ants interesting, even beyond
ant keeping hobbyists. From reading your
comments, a lot of you seem to really
[music] like ants. It's actually kind of
amazing how many people barely find
biology interesting besides ants. But I
guess I'm not surprised. I remember as a
child noticing ants crowding around the
crack of a sidewalk and apparently they
were fighting an entire war right on the
pavement beneath [music] my feet. I
remember dropping a piece of food and
coming back to it minutes later to see
hundreds of ants [music] swarming it and
carrying pieces of it off. Kneeling down
and observing them was one of those
things that made me interested in
biology. I was a weird kid. I stared at
a lot of bugs, but now I do that for
work. So, in a way, I owe my career to
ants. Ants are the only animals with
sophisticated [music]
organizations that rival or even surpass
human civilizations. [music]
So, it's incredible that so many
mercaphiles have evolved to exploit
them. Actually, it only makes sense. Ant
systems are so solid that they have room
to be exploited [music] and still be
completely fine. It would make less
sense if over the course of evolution,
no other organisms evolved to exploit or
work with them. Because animals evolve
based on their environments, [music]
and the presence of ants is ubiquitous
in nearly every environment. If every
ant were to die tomorrow, nearly every
ecosystem would collapse. If every other
animal were to die tomorrow, a lot of
ants [music] wouldn't even notice.
Thanks for watching.